A Guide to the Interfaith Council of Greater Richmond records, 1936-1999
Virginia Commonwealth University, James Branch Cabell Library
Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library
Interfaith Council of Greater Richmond records, 1936-1999
Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library, Virginia Commonwealth University
M321
5 linear feet.
Interfaith Council of Greater Richmond
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Donated by the Interfaith Council of Greater Richmond, VA in 2003
Historical Information
The Interfaith Council of Greater Richmond (ICGR) is an organization of 21 different religious denominations in the city of Richmond and surrounding counties. The 98 member congregations within these faith groups bring together diverse doctrinal, cultural and ethnic backgrounds.
Prior to 1900, community responsibilities for public welfare were assumed by volunteers from various religious groups. However, with the development of the profession of Social Work in the 1920s, many city governments began to employ public welfare workers. The need for communication among the public and private organizations, professionals, and volunteers in Richmond, VA led to the formation of the Richmond Council of Social Agencies in the early 1920s, and subsequently the Richmond Community Fund in 1924. Dr. Arthur Guild was the Executive Director of both groups.
There was confusion between the new social work professionals and the church members who traditionally had been responsible for helping those in need. The Council of Social Agencies along with the Richmond Ministerial Union saw the need for understanding and cooperation between the religious community and the social agencies. To address this need, the Rev. Dr. James C. Faw, a member of the Board of Directors for both agencies, turned to the women of the churches and synagogues who were already organized within their organizations. The recommendation passed and a subcommittee of the Council was established. Dr. Faw and Mr. Guild assisted women from three faiths - Protestant, Catholic and Jewish - to organize the Council of Church Women in 1929 as a Sub-Council of the Council of Society Agencies. This Council of Church Women was the first name of the Interfaith Council of Greater Richmond. Mrs. McClean Whittet became the first Chair.
In 1940, the name of the Council of Church Women was changed to The Interfaith Council of the Richmond Area Church Women to avoid confusion with The Women's Council of Churches, an existing Protestant group.
In 1979, The Interfaith Council of Richmond Area Church Women shortened its name to The Interfaith Council in order to reflect more clearly the diversity of religious traditions it represented. The Bah0xC3 0xA1'i Faith was the first expansion faith to join ICGR in the 1970s. In the same year, the Interfaith Council accepted an invitation to affiliate with the National Conference of Christians and Jews (NCCJ). In 1991-92, the Council added the Virginia Council of Churches (VCC) and the Virginia Interfaith Center for Public Policy to its circle of affiliations.
In 1986, the Interfaith Council changed its name to the Interfaith Council of Greater Richmond (ICGR) to expand its membership to the entire area. In 1991-92, representatives from Muslim, Sikh, Hindu, Buddhist, Jain, and American Baptist groups were welcomed into membership.
In 1983-84, a member of the Greek Orthodox Church and in 1991-92, a member of the Church of Jesus Christ of Latter Day Saints were elected President. The Board voted in January 1992 to incorporate all member religious organizations into the rotation for presidential election.
Scope and Content
The materials in this collection range from 1936 to 2004 and include correspondence, minutes, photographs, and numerous yearbooks from the Interfaith Council of Greater Richmond. The collection highlights the annual events and the meetings of the organization.
Arrangement
The collection is contained in albums arranged chronologically by each president's term.
Contents List
- 1936-1980 (Box 1)
- N.D. Materials [Found loose in box] N.D. (Box-folder 1:1)
  Correspondence
  Second Mile Stocking
  Members and Guests Registration
  Past Presidents
- Oldest Papers: Dr. Faw's File n.d., 1936, 1946, 1954, circa 1971 (Box-folder 1:2)
  Historical Sketch
  Minutes
  Notes
  Purpose and Standing Rules
  Past Presidents List
- 1945 (Box-folder 1:3)
  Education
  Family Relations
  Public Welfare
  Radio Broadcast
  Recreation and City Government
- 1946 (Box-folder 1:4)
- 1947 (Box-folder 1:5)
  Clippings
- 9 December 1949 - 10 May 1962 (Box-folder 1:6)
  Annual Reports, Correspondence, Minutes, Treasurer's Reports
- 1950 (Box-folder 1:7)
  Committee Members
- 1953 (Box-folder 1:8)
  Easter Sunday Broadcast, Minutes
- 1954 (Box-folder 1:9)
  Churches by Denomination, Correspondence, Program Theme
- 1955 (Box-folder 1:10)
  Correspondence, Minutes, Program Theme
- 1956 (Box-folder 1:11)
  Correspondence, Minutes
- 1957 (Box-folder 1:12)
  Correspondence, Journal Clippings, Minutes
- 1958 (Box-folder 1:13)
  Correspondence, Minutes, Representatives
- 1959 (Box-folder 1:14)
  Correspondence, Meeting Announcements, Minutes
- 1960 (Box-folder 1:15)
  Correspondence, Clippings, Minutes
- 1960-1980 (Box-folder 1:16)
  Certificates, Correspondence
- 1961 (Box-folder 1:17)
- 1961-1962 (Box-folder 1:18)
  Agenda, Correspondence, Minutes, Program Theme, Treasurer's Report
- 14 September 1962 - 9 May 1970 (Box-folder 1:19)
- 1962-1963 (Box-folder 1:20)
  Agenda, Correspondence, Minutes
- 1963-1970 (Box 2)
- September 1963 - May 1964 (Box-folder 2:1)
  Minutes, Correspondence